Amen. Amen. Amen. Well, it's a thrill to be here today. We serve a good God. Amen? Amen.
So, I don't know, this is the first time I've seen that, and I loved all of the death is defeated,
and the graves couldn't hold him, and those are all good newspaper articles for the resurrection
of Jesus, but on Easter Sunday, number one, that's not the news articles that were going
around. This is the third Sunday when we're dealing with the same day, and exactly, I think
next Sunday, Ryan will be preaching, and I think he's doing the road to Emmaus, and that's
also, it's the same day. Do you think it's an important day? Might have been. Might have
been. So, last week I talked about what do you do when you're worried and afraid, and
we looked at Mary Magdalene, the first person to be the risen Christ. He hadn't even ascended
to the Father yet, and Christ put his stamp of approval on all women as a testimony to who
he lived when Mary Magdalene was the first, but if you recall, there was still lots of fear
and lots of confusion. When she went back and told the disciples, they said, well, yes,
it couldn't be. They didn't believe it. Now, I know some of you engaged in the care of relinquishment,
and I know for some of you it was helpful, and some of you asked me for the slides, if you could
send those to me. I don't know if you know, but each one of our messages, we try to put
something about the message on our webpage under the blog section. And so, if you want those
steps of relinquishment, you can just go to canviscommunity.forks and go to the blog, and I think April wrote
the blog for that week, and then you can see those steps. You can also click on what's the message
you're given. Okay, so during the third week, same day, same fears, same losses, same anxieties, and yet people are starting to believe by the evening now. There are several appearances of Jesus.
Several appearances of Jesus, and now is the first large appearance of appearance to a whole group of people. Our text today is going to come out of John, but if we can, just to get context, if you have your Bible taken to Luke 24, I want to walk very quickly through Luke 24, 33 through 49, and then after walking through that, we're going to look at what then John says about this same occurrence.
It's wonderful. It's wonderful when you get a synoptic from John. John often doesn't deal with the same stuff that Matthew Mark and Luke does. He deals with a whole bunch of other stuff.
But every now and then, John says, yeah, what he said was good, but there's some more things that are important that you can't miss. I want you to know this so that you may believe that he is the Christ and has life in his name.
And so we're going to look at Luke 1, and then we'll look at the sort of synoptic part of that, the similar part of that in the Gospel of John.
So, I'm going to begin with verse 33. Before this, there are two guys on the road to Emmaus. Jesus goes up. They don't recognize him. He says, what's going on? They say, don't you know? Haven't you been? Where have you been?
I mean, it's the whole town is in the road. It's the Messiah, we believe, had come, and they killed him, and so Jesus talks with them, and then he begins to explain some of the pictures.
And at the very end, he breaks bread, and when he breaks bread, their eyes are opened, and they realize who he is.
And then, in his resurrected body, he just kind of vanishes. He goes somewhere else.
So, we pick up that story in verse 33. They got up and returned at once to Jerusalem.
There they found the eleven. By the way, if I said, I did such and such a week ago,
Do I mean, necessarily, that I did it seven exact days ago?
Probably not.
I might have done six days ago. I might have done eight days ago.
And I will say, a week ago.
In this case, when he says the eleven, there are actually only ten apostles.
Because Judas was no longer.
And he found out later that Thomas wasn't with them.
But the eleven was the apostles.
It was a grouping.
And so, they went to the eleven, and notice here, because this is important for when we look later in John.
John doesn't reference this, but Luke does.
They found the eleven, and those with them assembled together.
So, when they got back, there were the apostles minus Judas and minus Thomas,
and others with them, and then these two guys who had met Jesus on the road to Emmaus.
So, there's a group of them.
It's not just the apostles, but it's the followers of Jesus.
It's the human beings.
I mean, it's not the faithful.
It's the followers of Jesus.
It's the faithful.
Okay.
Trimble together and saying,
It is true.
The Lord has risen and has appeared to Simon.
And that's really interesting.
We're not quite sure if he's saying this.
Are the two guys to Emmaus saying it?
How would they know that he appeared to Simon?
Is Simon Simon Peter?
Or is one of those guys named Simon?
We don't have to.
But it sounds like Paul believes it's Peter,
because he later on talks about Jesus appearing to Peter.
So, we'll take that.
So, Jesus appeared to Mary Magdalene.
He's appeared to these two guys.
He's appeared to Peter.
And there's two guys.
They're telling the story.
They're in between what has happened on the way
and how Jesus was recognized by them when he broke bread.
And while they were still talking about this,
remember, they are locked in a room afraid of the Jews.
This is a scary day.
And we're starting to hear all these rumors of what has happened.
And some have believed and others have it.
And while they were still talking about this,
Jesus himself stood among me and said,
Peace be with you.
Now, this interesting thing, we'll see John, he repeats the peace be with you,
and I think he repeats it, because the fourth time it's just like a greeting.
It's, you know, hey, how you doing?
It's Cory saying, bro!
And they were startled.
And they were frightened.
Same thing they saw, a ghost.
And now, Jesus is going to want to make sure they get two things,
and get these two things clear.
The first one is that he has physically resurrected.
Now, his physical body is not like our physical body.
It's a glorified body, because he just kind of walks through walls.
He shows up, and then he goes other places.
He seems to be, it's almost like, you know, a star trip with a change porter.
He goes over here, and then he beams in over here.
And we don't fully get all the context of it.
But he wants to make sure that they know that he's not a ghost.
And so, he said, hey, look.
Look at my hand.
Look at my side.
Go ahead, touch me.
Notice that I am flesh and bones like you.
And then they make sure that they get it.
He said, do you have anything to eat?
I'm going to give him some fists, and this person may,
this person may be, this person may be, this person may be.
Okay?
So, the first thing that Jesus wants to make sure that they understand
is that this is a physical resurrection.
It's a bodily resurrection.
It's an essential doctrine of the gospel.
That Jesus rose again from the dead bodily.
It's glorified.
It's different.
Your body is going to be different.
Yes, yes.
And everyone said, amen.
Yeah.
Hallelujah.
I can always count on you.
I love you up here in the sun.
That's awesome.
The second thing that he wants to make sure is that they get the essentials done.
So, one of the things I love about getting this community is that we really do work hard
at focusing on the essentials.
And we're trying to talk about the intricacies of theology.
We love it.
I know that Melissa has gone through the parables of Jesus.
And I know that Corey has gone through an anti-right book.
And just trying to look at other ways of understanding the totality of what God says.
And those conversations are important and they're good.
But I love that we can have those conversations and perhaps disagree on some of that stuff.
And yet, on the essential.
The essential.
I know that Ryan is working with a group of men and women right now to just discern and articulate what are our core practices.
What's essential to who we are?
How do we behave?
I think core practices and identifying them are really important.
They form a body when they're understood and known.
One of my favorite core practice stories.
How many of them have flown Southwest?
What do you know about Southwest when you get on and they go through the free flight truck?
They hear us.
They joke.
Yeah.
One of those three core practices is we have fun.
And when they first rolled that core practice out, one of their platinum member flyers wrote a letter to the CEO saying how disappointed he was with the way that they trivialized the safety check.
And that if they're going to trivialize the safety check, he would no longer be flying with them even though he's a platinum member.
And the CEO responded with a three-word letter.
We'll miss you.
Core practices are those things that you're willing to be punished for.
And I don't know how the group is going to articulate, but I'm pretty sure somewhere in there there will be something along the lines of we really focus on what's important.
We focus on the senses.
Now, they'll do it in a much better, more creative way, but I love that.
And so Jesus is now going to give us, give the apostles, ask the followers, all these folks, the essentials that he wants to make sure they get.
He's surprised we didn't get them already, but you know what it takes.
So you've got to say it and say it again and say it again.
It takes six to six.
And so Jesus, he has your attention now.
He's going through the bed and he gives you a sense of, why are you troubled and why do you doubt rise in your minds?
Look at my hands and my feet.
It is I myself.
Touch me and fear.
There's not as flesh and bones as you see I have.
When he said that he strode in his hands and feet.
And while they did not believe it because of joy and amazement, so now they're leaving from not believing because of fear to, like, you know, it's still confusing.
But great joy and amazement.
And they gave their peace to boil his face and laid it.
And then he said to them, this is what I told you.
This is what I told you when I was with you.
Everything must be fulfilled that is written about me in the law of Moses and the prophets and the Psalms.
That's four hands for the entire Old Testament.
So here's a central one.
We base our life on the Scriptures.
We base our belief structures on the Scriptures.
And while we need to continually come back to them, it's not a box of answers that we just pull out.
We need the Holy Spirit to reveal to us.
We need one another.
But the foundation of life and practice is the Scriptures.
Jesus wants to make that really clear.
Everything must be fulfilled as written about me in the law of Moses and the prophets.
He opened their minds so that they would understand the Scriptures.
This is what's written.
Number one, the Messiah must suffer.
The cross of Jesus Christ, the bold cross of our sins, our violation of God's law and rule and order.
God's justice poured out upon the Messiah to sit in our place.
The cross of Jesus Christ is essential.
He must suffer.
This must happen.
You know, it's always fascinating to me.
Well, I'll get to that later.
The best way I can illustrate this is it's as though, it's as though God is just and God is merciful.
God cannot dwell where there's sin and yet he wants to dwell with us.
And so he's in a quandary.
He's got to solve this quandary.
Because he can't dwell where there's sin and yet he wants to dwell with us.
The best realization I've ever heard of this is it's as though you're standing before a judge.
I mean, I remember the big, well, I'm going to say the hands.
I don't know.
When I was there, their chair and their chair, they're up there and you're down here.
I mean, everything in the room is made to realize how important they are and how much of a supplicant you are.
So it's as though you're standing before the judge.
And the judge looks down and says, guilty.
And your fine is $1 trillion.
But you can never tell me.
And then the judge gets up, takes off his road.
He says, I know you can never tell it, but I don't want to enjoy it.
And comes down off the bench and writes a $1 trillion check and pays your cash.
That's the case, folks.
That's the case.
This is what was written, the Messiah must suffer and rise from the dead the third day.
Last week we talked about this quite a bit.
There's a lot of ways of looking at it, but here's the bottom line.
The resurrection is the affirmation that God accepted the payment on the cross.
He overcame death with wife.
Non-negotiable.
The Scriptures, the cross, Jesus is risen from the dead.
By the way, this is a side issue.
Who raised Jesus from the dead?
Don't be quick to eat it.
It's a bit of a trick question.
This is one of my favorite illustrations of the Trinity.
It says the Scriptures say the Father raised Jesus.
The Scriptures also say the Spirit raised Jesus.
And when Jesus was talking with him, he talked about his body as a temple.
He said, destroy this temple and I will raise it.
The Father of Jesus from the dead.
The Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
One God, three places.
This isn't an opportunity.
That's another essential doctrine, which Ryan will get to at some time.
Or maybe he'll assign it to Corey or Kenneth or someone else.
Okay.
I'm going to suffer, rise from the dead before the day and repenting for the forgiveness of sins.
The reason for this is because we are sinners.
And God wants to offer us the opportunity to turn from that thing and get to the dead.
Someone was telling me about some preacher, and I don't know if you know the preacher, forgive me,
that was debating whether or not you had to repent to be saved, whether you could just believe.
And so, believing means, it means not believing that and believing this.
It's like saying, can you turn to God without turning to God?
Repentance is the act of believing.
It's, I believe in you.
I don't believe in this.
I no longer believe in me.
I no longer believe in this ways of the world.
I believe in you.
I turn from that.
I turn to you.
So, he says, here's the essential piece, that you can repent, and you can be forgiven.
Then he was on to say, repent, repentance and forgiveness will be free in his name, in his name, to all the nations.
Jesus is talking to his followers, hey guys, I'm doing this for you.
But it's not just for you.
Just like with Abraham, that in Genesis 12, he talks about that he would bless Abraham.
But he would bless Abraham to be the father of a nation that would be the father of many nations.
I'm blessing you to be a blessing.
I'm doing this thing in you so that you can then take it elsewhere.
So, it's into the essential piece.
By the way, it's essential piece that I fear, in practice, we often blame, which is unfortunate, because when Jesus was talking about what's essential here, this is one of them.
This good news, this gospel.
Now, I might say you have to knock on doors and tell everyone that you don't know, but I hope your life is lived in such a way that at least someone asked you about it, and I hope that someone asked you about it, and you can at least say, excuse me.
Excuse me.
I'm not cooperating, but it's one of them.
This is an essential part that Jesus is saying, I want to make sure you get.
And that's, remember I said that it's not just the eleven.
It's all the other ones in Jesus, who are gathered together, this time, living in fear, living in anxiety, not going out and telling anyone, hiding from anyone that you might be able to tackle.
And Jesus said it is essential, that the Scriptures be fulfilled, that the Messiah, special and I, will be raised again from the dead, so that repentance and forgiveness might be not just offered, but preached and preached to all the nations.
It's essential piece.
Beginning at Jerusalem, you are witnesses of these things.
And then he said, and I'm going to say to you what my father has promised, to stay in the city until you're being clothed with powerful wonderful nights.
And we know from the rest of the Scriptures that you can't do this on your own, you don't need the Holy Spirit.
And in this particular passage, he tells them, and just wait until the Holy Spirit is poured out.
Fifty days later, on Pentecost, the Holy Spirit is poured out, the church is born, they are empowered to actually take the gospel into all the world.
Okay.
That's Luke.
Any questions?
Okay.
Turn to John.
John chapter 20.
And this is where I really want to hang out.
And we're going to start with verse 19.
Oh, wait.
One of the things I love about notes is very, if you get to say something and you see it in the notes.
Notice, we take the gospel to the nations.
You are God's plan.
You're God's plan.
The church is God's plan to preach this message.
And he has no plan B.
There's no plan B.
Okay.
Now, we're going to get to John chapter 20, verse 19 to 23.
Remember, Jesus is writing, or John's writing later, much later than the synoptics.
He probably has copies of the synoptics, or at least he's read them, or he's heard them read.
So, he's familiar with what he's reading.
He's writing a gospel.
Another picture of who this Jesus is.
And it's much shorter, but I think it's fascinating.
On the evening, verse 19, chapter 20, on the evening of that first day of the week, when the disciples were together with the doors locked, the fear of the Jewish leaders.
See, this is still this, this is the release of what's going on in this happen.
Jesus came and stood among them and said, peace be with you.
Right.
And he said this.
He showed them his hands in his side, and the disciples were overjoyed when they saw the Lord.
Again, Jesus said, and now he repeats them.
So, he's trying to say, hey, this isn't just a greeting.
This isn't just for all.
He's trying to say, Jesus, peace be to you.
Peace be to you.
Peace be with you.
And then he said two things that he kind of added to Luke's account.
And there's these two things that I want to try to illustrate today for us, because I think they're critical and important.
The first, as the Father has sent me, so I'm sending you.
I'm going to deal with that one second.
The second one that I'm going to deal with first.
And he said, he grieved on them and said, receive the Holy Spirit.
If you forgive anyone, they're sins.
Your sins are forgiven.
If you do not forgive them, they are not forgiven.
This is one of those passages that gives my Baptist friends connections.
And my Pentecostal friends get excited.
And I don't want to build a theological structure.
All Baptist friends, don't worry.
Pentecostals, be sad.
I'm not going to build a structure.
Because I think we often take the Scriptures and we try to build a systematic theology rather than take the Scriptures and look what does the Bible say and how do I now behave because of it.
Here's the, we also talked about the biblical theology of what does the Bible say and on top of that it's systematic theology.
And I like systematic theology.
I have several of them in my office.
I refer to them all the time.
But the systematic theology is the attempt of taking all of these biblical theological truths and putting them into something coherent that we can understand as, here's a mate, guys.
He's what he wants your ways.
Who can know the mind of God.
Now, I'm not telling you the systematic theology of God.
It's wonderful.
It's great.
I love it.
I embrace it.
I receive it.
But what the Bible does, because you have biblical theology, you have systematic theology, and on top of that, this is what I taught in the seminary.
Perks of theology.
Here's the deal, folks.
The Bible, the Bible teaches biblical theology and text of theology.
Now, we, because we have this need to talk to him and know and understand and be able to, to be on number one, we're right.
We build our systems.
And again, I'm not saying this border systems are bad.
But I think if we're going to be biblical, we have to be humble here and absolute here and here.
And if it's the thing down here I struggle to reconcile, live in that struggle, that's okay.
The question becomes, but now what do I do?
So, on this one, rather than build a system of the Holy Spirit, a system I see all of you, can we just acknowledge that the Spirit of God is a person?
The Spirit of God is not a thing.
It's not a force.
The Spirit of God is a person.
And the Bible uses a lot of different metaphors to try to understand how we relate to the Holy Spirit.
The Bible uses the metaphors of wind.
And in this case, you find you're using on them.
And then on Pentecost, it's like a mighty rusting wind.
But the Bible also uses the image of water.
And so, I found that adults are best taught the way children are, with object lessons.
So, I have an object lesson for us today on the Holy Spirit and our relationship with the Holy Spirit.
And my brother, Corey, has agreed to volunteer for my illustration.
So, Corey, if you can come on up here.
Come on.
Okay.
So, one thing the Holy Spirit does.
Just look for you some.
It's perfect.
Come on, a little harder.
Okay, let me get my face.
Let me get my face.
Perfect.
So, one of the things the Holy Spirit does is convict.
And the Holy Spirit convicts believers in unbelievers.
Conviction is an external thing.
So, if we do water, it's kind of like, look at this.
And we respond.
You feel it.
You know it.
Okay?
So, wait.
Are you okay?
You still love me?
No.
In 1 Corinthians, it talks about that we drink of one spirit.
That the Spirit of God...
It's water.
Oh, that's it.
It really...
No.
Oh, come on.
This is drinks.
When you drink, the Spirit engulfs you.
The Spirit fills you.
It talks about that we are the temple of the Holy Spirit.
There's two places.
One place, the temple of the Holy Spirit is you.
It's the church.
The other place, it's me.
It's my body.
And so, you take the Holy Spirit with you and you.
You're...
Okay.
The third one, and...
The third one is baptized in the Holy Spirit.
And I know people like each other, when you start to use these words, it's biblical.
So, the word baptized literally means immersed.
It means immersed.
And so, we can have a relationship with the Holy Spirit where he's convicted of us.
We also have a relationship with the Holy Spirit where we receive the Holy Spirit, we take the Holy Spirit in, we drink of the Spirit.
But in baptized with the Holy Spirit, it means immersed in the Holy Spirit.
And in this context, it's not so much the Spirit in me as me in the Spirit.
If you look at...
The Scriptures talk about filled with the Holy Spirit.
It signs that we are filled.
Other times in the Scriptures, the metaphor is that the room is filled.
And so, the Holy Spirit just encompasses all of us.
But it's interesting.
The word baptized, according to the Greek, is also used for the word pickling.
I love the Lord's tradition.
That you get pickles in the Holy Spirit.
And if you are an egg, you're still an egg.
But you take on all the properties and principles of the bride.
If you're a cucumber, you're still a cucumber.
But I can tell you, my mother-in-law used to make some mighty good pickles.
And if you turn those little cucumbers into something that you would die for.
And they were all awesome.
Because it says, I've infused the price.
And then I had a woman in my congregation who used to pick with beans and garlic and broccoli.
And I begged her to bring me some.
They were so good.
It says, I was infused.
The Bible talks about being filled with the Holy Spirit.
You don't have to drink with wine, but be filled with the Holy Spirit.
But there is a sense of alcohol.
You're still you, but you don't ask like you anymore.
So too is the Holy Spirit.
That when you're blinded, when you're tickled, when you're immersed in the Holy Spirit.
And in this one, there really is much more of the Spirit is all over.
They will never forget.
I do.
You guys want to see that one?
Who wants to see it?
Thank you very much.
You know, when I worked at the Judicated Jews, we would go to various national parks or state
parks in this country.
And one of them was right on the border of the Mississippi.
And we used to love this one.
And when you were playing the Mississippi all day.
And when you were playing the Mississippi, if you were in up to your ankles, you could go up and down and all over the place.
If you got into your waist, you were over time moving the direction of the river.
But if you got in, and you were no longer touching your great hands, if you were fully immersed, I mean, I played in Junior Olympics.
But I was a good friend.
You cannot beat the Mississippi.
Right?
When you immersed in the Spirit of God.
And here's where I think the systems fall down.
We try to define a system by saying, you know, when did it happen?
How much will it happen?
What does it mean?
What does it look like?
And we build these systems.
And here's the problem.
If the Spirit is sprinkling you, pay attention.
If you're thirsty, take a drink.
If you're out on the beach running, you've been in the water, you've been in the middle of a river,
but you've gotten fire in the river, and you don't like where it's taking in,
and you don't want to go there again, and so you get out, you kind of play around on the shore,
and you start playing with sand capsules, get back in the river.
Immerse yourself in the Spirit of God, that the Spirit of God might lead you.
The first place is not defined as people who were saved and filled with the Spirit.
The Spirit of God may be having these moments of intense pickering in the Holy Spirit.
The language of the Holy Spirit.
This friend of mine used to say, I actually wrote it.
He said, you know what?
You get as much of the Holy Spirit as you're ready for when you're ready for.
I love that.
Okay.
The second one is, as the Father has sent me, so send on you.
And for this, we're going to move into a time of communion.
But let me talk about it a little bit, because I think communion is probably one of the best illustrations of, as the Father has sent me, so send on you.
So, Jesus, on the night he was betrayed, chose the bread, and he blessed the bread.
And then he broke the bread, and he broke it so that he might be able to give the bread.
Right?
So, Henry and the Owen said, Jesus is the bread of life.
And the Father chose Jesus.
The Father broke Jesus.
And the Father broke Jesus.
So, here's the gospel, folks.
I know we always, you know, who killed Jesus?
No, it was the Romans.
I mean, yeah.
It was the Jews.
Yeah.
It was us.
But it's the gospel.
It was the Father.
The Lamb was slain from the foundation of the world.
Isaiah tells us that it pleads the Lord to bruise him.
It pleads the Lord not because he statistically wants to bruise his son, but because he wants the punishment.
Praise so that he can be in a relationship with you.
Jesus was chosen, and he was blessed, and he was broken.
And you know, again.
Again, here in the Owen says this.
You were up there, too.
God has chosen you.
He's chosen you.
We don't get in by a lane's will.
No one comes to the Father except the Father's daughter.
And again, I'm not building a system that I feel like you.
I'm just telling you that you can't be good enough for God.
When you were unlovable, he loved you.
When you were unredeemable, he redeemed you.
He chose you.
And when he chose you, he blessed you.
He blessed you.
And he continues to bless you.
You are not an accident.
You're a divine choice that's been blessed.
But here's what's fortunate or fortunate truth.
He chose you and blessed you if you might be grateful.
And the Father sent me, so did he send me you.
I often don't like it.
But the most transformative moment in my life has been in the good.
And the All Saints come to God, so did you even in your work schedule?
He's working to make you more like you.
We are chosen and blessed.
And often, some of our own grace is specifically so that we might be given.
Paul says in 2 Corinthians, it's the comfort you've received, comfort of it.
It's what you've gotten good.
Now, I know there are times when we have seen a communion like an altar call.
And if you want to say yes to Jesus, if you've never said yes to Jesus,
Jesus is offering us, bring grace.
And I'm going to invite you to come and take that.
But today, for those of you who are already known by the Lord,
and because of that, you know the Lord.
I'm going to invite you to this community.
It's going to be a moment of you not just receiving what he has done for you today,
but accepting the reason he's done it for you.
He has chose you and blessed you that you might be broken to be given.
This is what I mean to the kingdom, Lord.
I've been dancing around on the side, building my family castles,
dipping my foot in the water every Sunday.
It's nice.
And if I feel it's a particularly spiritual, I'll go on Wednesday night to Bible study.
And the rest of the week, it'll just move on down.
Father, we thank you for this symbol.
And, Lord, I count it all joy when we encounter various styles,
because I know you have a plan.
You have a purpose.
I know it produces patience and character and hope that you never disappoint.
So, Lord, as we come to the table, here are fights.
We receive the choice of your blessing.
But we also receive what you need to do to give us,
that we might be a vessel of your spirit,
for your work as a kingdom outposts and a kingdom outposts.
There are two spots in the bank.
There's a spot up here.
I mean, I'm not going to tell you which way to go,
because this thing messed it all up.
Amen.
If it takes you longer to get to the table,
that's God's gift to you to take a little more time
and instruct what he's saying.
Feel free to go back.
Feel free to come forward.
Feel free to sit.
There's no judgment between you and all to take communion.
But if you take communion, you're saying yes to God.
The table is open.
I promise you, God.
Thank you.